I've become accustomed due to so many
studies pointing in one direction to
seeing the Mediterranean diet do all
kinds of good for human health, but
today may be an exception, at least in a
relative sense. I've been doing uh more
research into arthritis lately, and
according to one randomized control
trial, another diet, a low carbohydrate
diet, may be the antidote to arthritis
that the Mediterranean diet is not.
We'll get into why as well as what to
take away from this study because there
are some intriguing reasons why.
Psoriasis is the most common
autoinflammatory disease in the world
and it's a multiffactorial condition as
with many, but it's generally
characterized as an overactivation of
immune cells, especially T- helpper
cells and TH7 T- cells. So these are
part of our more specialized adaptive
immune system that invade into our skin
as one site at least. Once activated,
these uh cells mass-produce inflammation
molecules called cytoines like
interlucan 1, interlucan 6, 23 for
dendritic cells, 22, 17 and other
cytoines. This uh overp production of
these molecules leads to hyperp
proliferation and angioenesis in more
understandable terms mass production of
skin cells. So keratinocytes that leads
to the buildup of immature skin cells
creating that scaly plaque looking
formation on the skin that some people
experience in psoriasis. Now the
relationship to arthritis is a similar
infiltration that can occur in the
joints leading to the activation of
synenovioittes cells in the joint
responsible for producing the
lubricating fluid in your joints called
synenovial fluid as well as collagen and
different proteins that make up your
joint structure. If these cells
proliferate aggressively, they can form
a much thicker layer in the joint that
invades into the cartilage and pushes
against the bones, breaking down those
structures to make room in effect. So it
disturbs the integrity of the joint. So
the big picture is if we can reduce this
uh specific inflammatory cascade
surrounding these tea cells, we might be
able to prevent these skin and joint
issues from happening. So in this study,
the researchers recruited overweight
people with seroriatic arthritis in
their 50s and had them follow two diets.
So for eight weeks, they were instructed
to consume a ketogenic or very low
carbohydrate diet and then they did a
wash out where they returned to their
previous diet for 6 weeks and after
those six weeks they were placed on a
Mediterranean diet. This is called a
crossover design because the same
participants are exposed to both diets.
We'll discuss some nuances of both diets
later on as well. So, the researchers
measured a bunch of inflammatory
cytoines before and after each diet, as
well as even more importantly, arthritis
symptoms. Unsurprisingly, both diets led
to significant improvements in weight,
fat mass, visceral fat, improved liver
enzymes, and more. But there were
largely no differences between groups.
And that's important because whatever
differences we might see between the
diets on the seroriatic arthritis front
would speak to the direct effects of the
diet components not due to the
additional weight loss or some other
factor. Okay. Now if we start with the
arthritis symptoms measured by two
scales the psoriasis area and severity
index or the posi and the disease
activity index of seroriatic arthritis
or dapsa. The lower the score, the less
symptoms and the better the quality of
life. Looking at that data, we have the
baseline measurement before being on
either diet on the left side and then
the MD for the Mediterranean diet, KD
for the ketogenic diet. And if the P
values there go under 0.05, that means
that there's a statistically significant
identified effect. So when comparing the
baseline against the Mediterranean diet,
the diet provided no benefit. We'll
return to that in just a bit. However,
when comparing the ketogenic diet in
both measures, the ketogenic diet
reduced arthritis symptoms. Then,
although not shown here, but shown here,
comparisons between the two diets also
indicate a ketogenic advantage. Now, if
we return to these data, people with a
bit of stats knowledge will likely
notice the extremely large lines here.
Now, in many studies, those would be
standard error measurements. And for
standard error, those are huge. But
they're actually reporting standard
deviation. So the uh spread of the data
which is wider than standard error.
Anyway, the point remains that this
study was small, only 16 individuals. So
it's possible that we're missing an
effect in the Mediterranean diet that
we'd see if we'd even doubled the number
of people in the study since we'd be
increasing the amount of data that we
could input. Regardless, it seems
unlikely that we'd lose this keto
advantage. Still, there are some nuances
to the keto diet that we'll need to
address shortly. We have a lot more to
cover, including uh why the ketogenic
diet is able to improve seroriatic
arthritis, but I'm going to be going
into more in-depth in the full version
of this video, which is available for
the Physionic Insiders, along with uh
detailed written breakdowns, uh
shortened summaries, a private podcast,
live sessions with me, and more. If
you're interested in having access to
complete access to all my research along
with joining a community of people who
follow a series of different diets
including ketogenic, uh, Mediterranean,
and more. Check out the Physionic
Insiders in the description box. So, one
thing the researchers point out is that
a major ketone, a molecule produced by a
very low carbohydrate diet like
ketogenic, can inhibit something inside
our cells called the inflammosome. The
inflammosome is a complex of proteins
that activates a pro-inflammatory
protein called a caspace. This caspace,
specifically caspace 1, cleaves immature
pro-inflammatory cytoines like the ones
that we discussed earlier and it turns
them into their final form, golden
frieza. No, their fully mature version
like a fully functional interlucan
protein. The ketone beta hydroxybutyrate
reduces the formation of this
inflammosome complex by blocking one of
its adapter proteins from forming. That
may offer a specific advantage of the
ketogenic diet versus the Mediterranean
diet. Like I said, I'll be describing
more on the mechanisms in the full
version of this video, but that's the
most unique one in relation to ketogenic
diets. Of course, all this is contingent
on us seeing actual reductions in these
inflammatory molecules like we discussed
since they are the origin source or
close to it of this psoriasis and
arthritis effect. So what happens? Well,
looking at interlucan 6 on the left and
interlucan 17 on the right, we clearly
see that the ketogenic diet reduces
both. Yet the Mediterranean diet fails
to do so. This is also the case when
looking at other interlucan
measurements. But surprisingly, the
researchers didn't measure interlucan 1,
which is the primary interlucan produced
by the inflammosome pathway that we just
went over. It would have really been
nice to see instead of speculating on
the mechanism. Now, I did mention some
additional details related to these
diets and some context to be applied.
Okay, so the ketogenic diet specifics
weren't made overly clear, but the
researchers did encourage unsaturated
fats like olive oil. though it might be
reasonable to assume, although
unconfirmed, that the ketogenic diet
leaned toward unsaturated fats instead
of saturated fats. In addition, they did
emphasize vegetable consumption to make
up that 30 to 50 grams of carbohydrates
that participants were allowed to eat.
The Mediterranean diet was of course
also focused on unsaturated fats from
olive oil and fatty fish and nuts and
low intakes of red meat and generally of
saturated fats. carbohydrates were whole
grains, vegetables, legumes, and fruits.
Oh, also one more thing. If we pull up
the data again on the arthritis symptoms
themselves, I just like to point out
that the effect size is pretty
tremendous. Something like a 50%
reduction, which is also possibly why
such a small sample size was able to
detect a difference, but it's still a
small study and the majority of the
participants were women. So, what can we
take away from this study?
Well, this randomized control trial
indicates a ketogenic diet likely
unsaturated fat focused is superior to a
Mediterranean diet for massively
reducing seroriatic arthritis symptoms
and inflammation in overweight
middle-aged individuals suffering from
seroriatic arthritis. If this holds up
in other studies, this is a really
impressive result. You know, something
that really bothers me about all this is
the fact that we're at the end of the
video and you haven't checked out this
upcoming video here. We should keep
hanging out over there. Thanks for
joining. See you over there.